A Guide to the Blue Ridge Sanatorium Collection 1920 - 1984
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
Blue Ridge Sanatorium, 1920-1984
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-12
7 linear ft. (15 boxes); correspondence, reports, minutes, administrative documents, and other archival material.
Collected from Blue Ridge Hospital.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Joan Echtenkamp Klein, Assistant Director for Historical Collections and Services, acquired material from James S. Kennan, Administrator of Blue Ridge Hospital, in 1986.
Biographical/Historical Information
Blue Ridge Sanatorium opened on April 26, 1920 just outside of Charlottesville, Virginia. It was funded by a mill tax passed by the Virginia General Assembly in 1918. 1/8 of the funds raised by this tax were designated for prevention and eradication of tuberculosis. The State Board of Health was charged with administration of these funds. Catawba Sanatorium had been operating for nearly ten years with a lengthy waiting list. Piedmont Sanatorium opened outside of Burkeville in 1918 for African Americans. The Charlottesville area welcomed Blue Ridge Sanatorium by donating $15,000.00 toward the purchase of land and construction, and by offering to supply free city water to the sanatorium for its first five years of operation. Proximity to the University of Virginia Hospital added to the attractiveness of the location.
The Addison, Strode, and Thomas pavilions were constructed in 1919 to house patients, with men assigned to the Strode pavilion, and women to the Addison pavilion. When children were added to the patient population in 1922, they lived in the Thomas Pavilion. Rooms in the pavilions were connected to long porches where patients sat during the day and slept at night. Fresh air was considered a vital element in the curative regimen, which also included rest, moderate exercise, and a diet of fresh fruits, vegetables, milk and reduced animal protein. Early treatments also included the use of an Alpine lamp, a type of sun lamp believed to assist in the cure of tuberculosis. Patients organized the Cheer-Up Club to raise funds for needy patients, to purchase victrolas and records, and sponsor concerts for patients and staff.
Trinkle Infirmary was built in 1922. A chapel was added several years later, and the George W. Wright Memorial Pavilion was erected in 1927 with funds raised by the Grand Lodge of Masons of Virginia. A teacher joined the staff in 1923 to help resident children keep up in school. In 1937 an adult Rehabilitation School opened to help patients improve their economic circumstances upon release. To help with staffing, a training school for nurses was started in July of 1920 with one nurse in the first graduating class. In 1933, the training school for tuberculosis nurses established a formal affiliation with the Nurses Training School of the University of Virginia. The final graduating class of the Blue Ridge Nurses Training School held commencement exercises on May 24, 1962.
W. E. Brown oversaw much of the growth and changes at the sanatorium in his 23 year tenure as Superintendent from 1921 until 1944. During the years of the Great Depression, food was scarce and many people with symptoms of tuberculosis could not afford to apply for treatment. They waited until their cases were significantly advanced with less likelihood of a cure. The number of admissions of patients with advanced cases increased. At the same time over 1/3 of the patients discharged cited lack of ability to pay the $7.00 weekly fee as their reason for leaving, even when they were not considered cured. In 1932 the sanatorium purchased adjacent land which it used for farming and for establishment of a dairy herd to supply fresh milk to patients. In 1939 a new infirmary, the East Wing, was constructed with funds from a WPA grant to address the increase in advanced non-ambulatory cases.
World War II saw a drastic shortage in supplies and staff, as rationing reduced the quantity and quality of food products available, and the war created a shortage of nurses, orderlies and other trained workers. In 1943 an "Honor Camp" of penitentiary prisoners were put to work in the cafeteria. Screening for Selective Service resulted in identification of early cases of tuberculosis and more patients were admitted with less advanced cases. Interns from the University of Virginia entered into three month rotations at Blue Ridge, learning to perform "chest work" such as pneumothorax. This process involved using a needle to deliberately collapse the infected lung in order to give it time to heal and contain the lesion within. While diet and environment were never discounted as key aspects of treatment, surgical intervention became increasingly important. E. Cato Drash and other surgeons from the University of Virginia performed thoracic surgery on a growing number of patients. Frequently doctors and nurses diagnosed with tuberculosis came to Blue Ridge as patients and stayed on as employees.
In the early 1950's, new drugs were developed to assist in the cure of tuberculosis. These included isonicotinic acid hydrazide, streptomycin, para-aminosalicylic acid (PAS) and isoniazid. There was a steady decline in the waiting list for the sanatorium as more people remained at home and received drug therapy from their family doctors. In 1954, for the first time in its history, the sanatorium had vacancies for women. The average age of admitted patients was higher than previously, presenting additional challenges in addressing the health needs of an older patient population. In 1965 African Americans were admitted to Blue Ridge for the first time upon the closing of Piedmont Tuberculosis Sanatorium. In 1970 various proposals to expand Blue Ridge Sanatorium programs beyond treatment of tuberculosis surfaced. These included the integration of alcoholics with trustee prisoners into a program of work and rehabilitation.
The construction of Interstate 64 in 1968 cut through the sanatorium property and the farmland across the highway was deeded to the city of Charlottesville, the future site of Piedmont Virginia Community College. In 1978, title to the Blue Ridge Sanatorium property was transferred to the University of Virginia and it was renamed Blue Ridge Hospital. Tuberculosis patients continued to receive treatment there, but additional University of Virginia medical center programs were also located on the site. These included obesity and diabetic clinics as well as the outpatient division of the Department of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry. The University of Virginia LPN program relocated to Blue Ridge in 1979, and the Institute of Law, Psychiatry, and Public Policy was also located there.
Scope and Content Information
The Blue Ridge Sanatorium collection includes Annual Reports from 1921 to 1970, correspondence with the State Health Director, State Board of Health minutes from 1922 to 1972, staff conference minutes, nurse and intern records, and procedural manuals for the sanatorium. Project plans about the transfer of the facility to the University of Virginia in 1978, agendas and minutes from 1978 to 1981, budget plans from 1955 to 1984, and reports of the Institute of Law, Psychiatry and Public Policy are also included.
Special Note: This collection complements the American Lung Association of Virginia Collection also available at this site. An additional site of interest concerning the redevelopment of the Blue Ridge Sanatorium property is http://www.faculty.virginia.edu/blueridgesanatorium.
Contents List
- BLUE RIDGE HOSPITAL PROGRAM PROJECT PLAN (ORIGINAL COPY) BY VAMIK D. VOLKAN, MEDICAL DIRECTOR 1979, MARCH, 210 TMs (Box-folder 01-001)
- ADMINISTRATIVE STAFF CONFERENCE PRESIDED OVER BY THOMAS V. SELLARS, FORREST W. PITTS 1977, 39 TMsS (Box-folder 01-002)
- ADMINISTRATIVE STAFF CONFERENCE PRESIDED OVER BY THOMAS V. SELLARS 1976, 44 TMsS (Box-folder 01-003)
- ADMINISTRATIVE STAFF CONFERENCE PRESIDED OVER BY THOMAS V. SELLARS 1975, 38 TMsS (Box-folder 01-004)
- ADMINISTRATIVE STAFF CONFERENCE PRESIDED OVER BY THOMAS V. SELLARS, FORREST W. PITTS 1974, 34 TMsS (Box-folder 01-005)
- ADMINISTRATIVE STAFF CONFERENCE PRESIDED OVER BY THOMAS V. SELLARS AND FORREST W. PITTS 1973, 37 TMsS (Box-folder 01-006)
- ADMINISTRATIVE STAFF CONFERENCE PRESIDED OVER BY THOMAS V. SELLARS AND FORREST W. PITTS 1972, 20 TMs, 31TMsS (Box-folder 01-007)
- ADMINISTRATIVE STAFF CONFERENCE PRESIDED OVER BY FORREST W. PITTS 1971, 32 TMsS, 20TMs (Box-folder 01-008)
- ADMINISTRATIVE STAFF CONFERENCE PRESIDED OVER BY FORREST W. PITTS 1970, 26 TMs, 16TMsS (Box-folder 01-009)
- ANNUAL REPORT CATAWBA SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY GRAHAM H. BOURHILL TO MACK I. SHANHOLTZ 1970, JUNE 30, 15 TMs (EC) (Box-folder 01-010)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM SUBMITTED BY RAYMOND S. BLACKMAN TO MACK I. SHANHOLTZ 1968, JUNE 30, 16 TMs (EC), 1 TL (Box-folder 01-011)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY CHARLES G. PEARSON TO MACK I. SHANHOLTZ 1969, JULY 1 - 1970, 3 AM, 1 TLS, 3 charts, etc. (Box-folder 01-012)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY CHARLES G. PEARSON TO MACK I. SHANHOLTZ 1961, JUNE 30, 3 Copies(24 TMs (EC) Each) etc (Box-folder 01-013)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY CHARLES G. PEARSON TO MACK I. SHANHOLTZ 1960, JUNE 30, 1 Copy (24TMs (EC)) (Box-folder 01-014)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM 1959, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (24 TMsS (EC)), etc. (Box-folder 02-001)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY CHARLES G. PEARSON TO MACK I. SHANHOLTZ 1958, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (22TMsS(EC) Each) (Box-folder 02-002)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY CHARLES G. PEARSON TO MACK I. SHANHOLTZ 1957, JUNE 30, 1 Copy (25 TMsS(EC)) (Box-folder 02-003)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY CHARLES G. PEARSON TO MACK I. SHANHOLTZ 1956, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (26 TMsS(EC)), 1TL (Box-folder 02-004)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY FRANK B. STAFFORD TO MACK I. SHANHOLTZ AND REPORT ON AUDIT BY J. GORDON BENNETT, AUDITOR OF PUBLIC ACCOUNTS, SUBMITTED TO THOMAS B. STANLEY, GOVERNOR OF VIRGINIA 1955, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (29 TMs(EC)), 2TLs etc. (Box-folder 02-005)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY FRANK B. STAFFORD TO MACK I. SHANHOLTZ 1954, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (31 TMs(EC)) 3TLs (Box-folder 02-006)
  COPIES SENT TO CHARLES W. SCOTT, PIEDMONT SANATORIUM AND CECIL C. SMITH, CATAWBA SANATORIUM
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY FRANK B. STAFFORD TO MACK I. SHANHOLTZ 1953, JUNE 30, 1 Report (24 TMs(EC)), etc. (Box-folder 02-007)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY FRANK B. STAFFORD TO MACK I. SHANHOLTZ 1952, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (25 TMs(EC)), 1 AM, etc. (Box-folder 02-008)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY FRANK B. STAFFORD TO STATE HEALTH COMMISSIONER AND REPORT ON AUDIT BY J. GORDON BENNETT, AUDITOR OF PUBLIC ACCOUNTS, SUBMITTED TO JOHN S. BATTLE, GOVERNOR OF VIRGINIA 1951, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (26 TMs(EC)), 2 TLs, etc. (Box-folder 02-009)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY FRANK B. STAFFORD TO L. J. ROPER 1950, JUNE 30, 3 Copies (2x27 TMs, 1x28 TMs) 2TLs (Box-folder 02-010)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY FRANK B. STAFFORD TO L. J. ROPER 1949, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (28 TMs), 10 TMs, etc. (Box-folder 02-011)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY FRANK B. STAFFORD TO L. J. ROPER AND REPORT ON AUDIT BY J. GORDON BENNETT, AUDITOR OF PUBLIC ACCOUNTS, SUBMITTED TO WILLIAM M. TUCK, GOVERNOR OF VIRGINIA 1948, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (25 TMs), 1 TL, etc. (Box-folder 02-012)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY FRANK B. STAFFORD TO L. J. ROPER 1947, JUNE 30, 3 Copies (23 TMs), 1 TL, 8 TMs (Box-folder 02-013)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY FRANK B. STAFFORD TO L. J. ROPER 1946, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (20 & 19 TMs), 11 TMs, etc. (Box-folder 02-014)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY FRANK B. STAFFORD TO I. C. RIGGIN 1945, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (19 TMs), 9 TMs, etc. (Box-folder 03-001)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY FRANK B. STAFFORD TO I. C. RIGGIN 1944, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (17 TMs), 1 TM, etc. (Box-folder 03-002)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO I. C. RIGGIN 1943, JUNE 30, 3 Copies (4 TMs), 2 Tables, etc. (Box-folder 03-003)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO I. C. RIGGIN 1942, JUNE 30, 3 Copies (4 TMs), 1 Table, etc. (Box-folder 03-004)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO I. C. RIGGIN 1941, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (4 & 5 TMs), 1 Table, etc. (Box-folder 03-005)
  CORRESPONDENCE WITH E. C. HARPER ON DEVELOPMENT OF COLLAPSE THERAPY TABLE
- SUPPORTING DOCUMENTATION FOR ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM 1940, JUNE 30, 1 Table (9 TMs) (Box-folder 03-006)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO I. C. RIGGIN 1939, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (4 TMs), 1 Table, etc. (Box-folder 03-007)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO I. C. RIGGIN 1938, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (4TMs), 2 Tables, etc. (Box-folder 03-008)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO I. C. RIGGIN 1937, JUNE 30, 1 Copy (5 TMs), 1 Table (9 TMs), etc. (Box-folder 03-009)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO I. C. RIGGIN 1936, JUNE 30, 1 Copy (6 TMs), 7 TMs, etc. (Box-folder 03-010)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO I. C. RIGGIN 1935, JUNE 30, 1 Copy (9 TMs), 1 Table, etc. (Box-folder 03-011)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO I. C. RIGGIN 1934, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (5 TMs), 1 Table, etc. (Box-folder 03-012)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO WARREN F. DRAPER AND CORRESPONDENCE BETWEEN W. E. BROWN AND W. A. PLECKER, REGISTRAR, BUREAU OF VITAL STATISTICS 1933, JUNE 30, 1 Copy (5 TMs), 2 Reports, etc. (Box-folder 03-013)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO WARREN F. DRAPER 1932, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (3TMs), 3 Tables, etc. (Box-folder 03-014)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO WARREN F. DRAPER 1931, JUNE 30, 3 Copies (3 TMs), 3 Tables, etc. (Box-folder 03-015)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO ENNION G. WILLIAMS 1930, JUNE 30, 4 Copies (3 TMs), 2 Tables, etc. (Box-folder 03-016)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO ENNION G. WILLIAMS 1929, JUNE 30, 1 Copy (4 TMs), 4 Tables, etc. (Box-folder 03-017)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO ENNION G. WILLIAMS 1928, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (9 TMs), 3 TLs, etc. (Box-folder 03-018)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO ENNION G. WILLIAMS 1927, JUNE 30, 1 Copy (8 TMs), 5 TMs (Box-folder 03-019)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO ENNION G. WILLIAMS 1926, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (11 TMs), 3 Tables, etc. (Box-folder 03-020)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO ENNION G. WILLIAMS 1925, JUNE 30, 2 Copies (8 TMs), 2 Tables, etc. (Box-folder 03-021)
- SUPPORTING DOCUMENTATION FOR ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM 1924, JUNE 30, 4 Tables (9, 5, 2 & 11 TMs each) (Box-folder 03-022)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO ENNION G. WILLIAMS AND CORRESPONDENCE ABOUT PREPARATION OF THE REPORT 1923, 2 Copies (17, 10 TMs), 6 TMs, etc. (Box-folder 03-023)
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO ENNION G. WILLIAMS AND DEPARTMENT OF COMMERCE, BUREAU OF THE CENSUS FORMS AND CORRESPONDENCE 1922, SEPTEMBER 30; 1921, SEPTEMBER 30, 1 Copy (18 TMs), 4 TMs, 8 TLS, etc. (Box-folder 03-024)
  ENNION G. WILLIAMS, STATE HEALTH COMMISSIONER
- ANNUAL REPORT BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM, SUBMITTED BY W. E. BROWN TO JOSEPH T. MASTIN 1921, SEPTEMBER 30, 11 TMs, 10 TL, 9 TLS, 1ALS, etc. (Box-folder 03-025)
  JOSEPH T. MASTIN, SECRETARY OF STATE BOARD OF CHARITIES AND CORRECTIONS TO WHOM THIS ANNUAL REPORT WAS SUBMITTED
- THERAPEUTIC AGENTS COMMITTEE 1974, JAN. 10-1978, AP. 6, 36 TMsS, 6 Articles, 1 Amemo, etc. (Box-folder 04-001)
  FORREST W. PITTS; THOMAS V. SELLARS
- BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM CLINICAL STAFF MEETING 1976, AP 14-1978, JUNE 1, 38 TMsS, 11 TMs (Box-folder 04-002)
  FORREST W. PITTS; BYRON W. MARSHALL
- MEDICAL AUDIT AND RECORDS COMMITTEE 1976, FEB. 27-1978, JE. 1, 49 TMsS, 51 TMs, 7 Charts, etc. (Box-folder 04-003)
  FORREST W. PITTS, THOMAS V. SELLARS, MICHAEL CAMPILONGO; INFORMED CONSENT
- BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE 1975, DEC. 11-1978, JE.1, 237 TMs(EC), 51 TMsS, 1AM, etc. (Box-folder 04-004)
  FORREST W. PITTS, THOMAS V. SELLARS, BYRON W. MARSHALL
- VIRGINIA BUDGET MANUAL FOR STATE AGENCIES 1978-1980, 29 TMs, 3 AMs, 1 Amemo (Box-folder 04-005)
- PROTECTIVE SERVICES (FOR USE IN WORKSHOP ONLY) 1978-1980, 9 TMs (Box-folder 04-006)
- MENTAL HEALTH SERVICES (FOR USE IN WORKSHOP ONLY) 1978-1980, 13 TMs (Box-folder 05-001)
- GROUND TRANSPORTATION REGULATION (FOR USE IN WORKSHOP ONLY) 1978-1980, 51 TMs (Box-folder 05-002)
- REVENUE SOURCE CODE STRUCTURE, DEPTARTMENT OF ACCOUNTS, COMMONWEALTH OF VIRGINIA no date, 48 TMs (Box-folder 05-003)
- VIRGINIA BUDGET MANUAL, DEPARTMENT OF PLANNING AND BUDGET 1977, APRIL, 94 TMs (Box-folder 05-004)
- VIRGINIA BUDGET MANUAL, DEPARTMENT OF PLANNING AND BUDGET, AND RELATED DOCUMENTS 1978, JULY 1, 195 TMs (Box-folder 05-005)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH MEETINGS MINUTES AND LETTER FROM BYRON W. MARSHALL, JR. TO FORREST W. PITTS 1973, 37 TMs, 1 TLS (Box-folder 05-006)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH MEETINGS MINUTES 1972, 36 TMs (Box-folder 05-007)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH MEETINGS MINUTES AND LETTER FROM MACK I. SHANHOLTZ TO FORREST W. PITTS 1971, 39 TMs (Box-folder 05-008)
  TUBERCULOSIS TREATMENT TO BE PHASED OUT AT CATAWBA SANATORIUM; ALL NEW ADMISSIONS TO BE SENT TO BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM.
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH MEETINGS MINUTES 1970, 21 TMs (Box-folder 05-009)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH MEETINGS MINUTES 1969, 7 TMs (Box-folder 05-010)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH MEETINGS MINUTES 1968, 20 TMs, 1 Map (Box-folder 05-011)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH MEETINGS MINUTES 1967, 16 TMs (Box-folder 05-012)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1962, 5 TMs (Box-folder 05-013)
  CHARLES G. PEARSON
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1961, 5 TMsS (Box-folder 05-014)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1960, 4 TMsS (Box-folder 05-015)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1959, 5 TMsS (Box-folder 05-016)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1958, 6 TMsS (Box-folder 05-017)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1957, 6 TMsS (Box-folder 06-001)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1956, 7 TMsS (Box-folder 06-002)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1955, 17 TMsS (Box-folder 06-003)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1954, 6 TMsS (Box-folder 06-004)
  FRANK B. STAFFORD
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1953, 13 TMsS, 1 Pamphlet (Box-folder 06-005)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1952, 9 TMsS (Box-folder 06-006)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1951, 12 TMsS, 1 Newspaper advertisement (Box-folder 06-007)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1950, 6 TMsS (Box-folder 06-008)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1949, 13 TMsS (Box-folder 06-009)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1948, 8 TMsS (Box-folder 06-010)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1947, 10 TMs (Box-folder 06-011)
  FRANK B. STAFFORD, E. CATO DRASH
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1946, 6 TMsS (Box-folder 06-012)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1945, 5 TMsS (Box-folder 06-013)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING CORRESPONDENCE 1945, 2 TL (Box-folder 06-014)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES AND CORRESPONDENCE 1944, 5 TMsS, 2TLS (Box-folder 06-015)
  FRANK B. STAFFORD, W. E. BROWN, VINCENT W. ARCHER, COLGATE W. DARDEN, JR.
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES; PERSONNEL LISTS AND RELATED CORRESPONDENCE 1943, 16 TMsS, 6 TL, 5 TLS, etc. (Box-folder 06-016)
  W. E. BROWN, COLGATE W. DARDEN, JR., JOHN S. BATTLE
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES AND CORRESPONDENCE 1942, 5 TMs, 1 TL (Box-folder 06-017)
  W. E. BROWN, COLGATE W. DARDEN, JR.
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1941, 3 TMs (Box-folder 06-018)
  W. E. BROWN
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1940, 6 TMs (Box-folder 06-019)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES AND CONTRUCTION BIDS 1939, 15 TMs (Box-folder 06-020)
  W. E. BROWN, W. E. STAINBACK
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1938, 10 TMs (Box-folder 06-021)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES AND CORRESPONDENCE 1937, 7 TMs, 15 TL, 7 TLS, 1 Amemo (Box-folder 06-022)
  W. E. BROWN, I. C. RIGGIN, GEORGE C. PEERY, JOHN S. BATTLE, GUY R. HARRISON
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES AND CORRESPONDENCE 1936, 3 TM, 5 TL, 5 TLS (Box-folder 06-023)
  W. E. BROWN, I. C. RIGGIN, SETH BURNLEY, W. DAN HAYDEN
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES AND CORRESPONDENCE 1935, 6 TMs, 1 TL (Box-folder 06-024)
  W. E. BROWN, I. C. RIGGIN
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES AND CORRESPONDENCE 1934, 3 TMs, 2 TL, 1 TLS (Box-folder 06-025)
  W. E. BROWN, WARREN F. DRAPER, ABRAM P. STAPLES
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1933, 3 TM (Box-folder 06-026)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES AND CORRESPONDENCE 1931, 7 TMs, 4 TLS, 3 TL, 1 AM, etc. (Box-folder 06-027)
  W. E. BROWN, H. T. VAN NOSTRAND, JR., JOHN GARLAND POLLARD
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1930, 1 TL (EC), 4 TMs (Box-folder 06-028)
  W. E. BROWN, H. T. MARSHALL, FRANCIS P. VENABLE; MARGARET CANTEY VENABLE LIBRARY FUND
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1929, 5 TMs (Box-folder 06-029)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES 1928, 4 TMs, 1 AM, 3 TLs (Box-folder 06-030)
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES AND CONTRUCTION BIDS 1927, 20 TMs, 10 TLS, 3 TL, 1 Drawing (Box-folder 06-031)
  W. E. BROWN, ENNION G. WILLIAMS, F. W. KING, J. H. BRADFORD
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES AND CORRESPONDENCE 1926, 8 TM, 1 TLS (Box-folder 06-032)
  W. E. BROWN, EDWIN A. ALDERMAN, E. LEE TRINKLE
- STATE BOARD OF HEALTH COMMITTEE FOR BLUE RIDGE SANATORIUM MEETING MINUTES AND CORRESPONDENCE 1925, 22 TMs, 12 TLS, 2 TL (Box-folder 06-033)
  W. E. BROWN, E. LEE TRINKLE, T. J. ROBIINSON